<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Dan Hough</title>
 <link href="http://www.danielhough.co.uk/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://www.danielhough.co.uk/"/>
 <updated>2012-05-05T09:22:07-04:00</updated>
 <id>http://www.danielhough.co.uk/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Daniel Hough</name>
   <email>dan@danielhough.co.uk</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Gamifying Collaboration</title>
   <link href="http://www.danielhough.co.uk/blog/gamifying-collaboration"/>
   <updated>2012-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://www.danielhough.co.uk/blog/gamifying-collaboration</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Gamifying Collaboration&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;meta&quot;&gt;Published 26 April 2012 in London, UK&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days ago I published a post about &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/huddle-hack-day/&quot;&gt;Huddle&amp;#8217;s Hack Day&lt;/a&gt; and, since I didn&amp;#8217;t want to be too revealing, omitted the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, one of the hacks is very unlikely to ever be production-ready: mine. I managed to convince &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/#!/peteog&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pete&lt;/strong&gt;,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/#!/dawncarvell&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dawn&lt;/strong&gt;,&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/#!/bruja_averia&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marta&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to join me in creating a hack inspired by games of days gone by: a top-down, 2D &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RPG&lt;/span&gt; based on &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/huddle-apis&quot;&gt;Huddle&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;API&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/a&gt; Together, we came up with a complex idea for the game which had a premise for a story, a goal and some actions which The Player could take to achieve that goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The premise of the game is simple: The player arrives into work one day and his 2D, 8-bit Boss is nagging him to finish a document and get it approved by 6pm. The player knows that this isn&amp;#8217;t going to happen, but he also know that The Boss has a memory of only three items at once. If The Player can distract him with enough other documents so that The Boss forgets about The Player&amp;#8217;s original document by 6pm, he&amp;#8217;ll be off scott-free for another day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What we actually made&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 10 hours we had to make this game, we managed to get a working game based on a JS framework called &lt;a href=&quot;http://craftyjs.com/&quot;&gt;Crafty&lt;/a&gt; with a little guy moving around and interacting with stuff, including simple key-controlled menus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to find out what the boss&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;memory&amp;#8221; includes, we used the files &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huddle.com/blog/the-death-of-file-search-and-the-rise-of-predictive-push/&quot;&gt;recommended to him by Huddle.&lt;/a&gt; The player could perform actions from their little in-game computer to create documents which the boss would subsequently comment on and thus be distracted by, raising the document&amp;#8217;s position in his list of recommended documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the document goes off the list, you win the game &amp;#8211; good job! It worked, and the other Huddlers were very amused by the idea (as well as the stupid success music). It was a successful proof of concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumbnail&quot; href=&quot;/img/gamifying-collaboration-1.png&quot; rel=&quot;lightbox&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/gamifying-collaboration-1.png&quot; width=&quot;99&quot; height=&quot;71&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;thumbnail&quot; href=&quot;/img/gamifying-collaboration-2.png&quot; rel=&quot;lightbox&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/gamifying-collaboration-2.png&quot; width=&quot;99&quot; height=&quot;71&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;thumbnail&quot; href=&quot;/img/gamifying-collaboration-3.png&quot; rel=&quot;lightbox&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/gamifying-collaboration-3.png&quot; width=&quot;99&quot; height=&quot;71&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;thumbnail&quot; href=&quot;/img/gamifying-collaboration-4.png&quot; rel=&quot;lightbox&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/gamifying-collaboration-4.png&quot; width=&quot;99&quot; height=&quot;71&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What we wanted to make&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we sat in our initial 10-minute brainstorming and planning session, it was difficult not to get distracted by the possibilities of this game. All of the following is what we said we&amp;#8217;d do if we exceeded our expectations and got stuff done a lot quicker. I&amp;#8217;ve provided links to Huddle&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; Documentation to indicate how the entire game could be powered by Huddle&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;API&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The player walks into the office and heads to his desk. As he sits down, he spots a &amp;#8220;note&amp;#8221; on his desk, which is actually taken directly from the Huddle &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; endpoint for &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/huddle-apis/wiki/UserApprovals#Retrieving_user_approvals&quot;&gt;User Approvals&lt;/a&gt; which shows what open approvals the authenticated user has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His one assignment, which is due by the end of the day, is for a document called &lt;strong&gt;The Report&lt;/strong&gt;. The Boss (an &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-player_character&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;NPC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) approaches The Player and tells him that if he doesn&amp;#8217;t get The Report done by the end of the day then he&amp;#8217;ll be fired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Player has some friends in the office, and after being given a shouting by The Boss, The Friend walks over and reassures The Player that since The Boss only has enough brain power to remember three things at once, if The Player can distract him with three other documents by the end of the day then maybe he&amp;#8217;ll be okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the top-right corner of the screen The Player suddenly sees a list of documents (numbered 1, 2 and 3) currently containing only one at the top spot &amp;#8211; the document assigned to him. By default, we&amp;#8217;ll make sure that this document has a really high recommendation score (I can&amp;#8217;t link to details on our recommendation engine &amp;#8211; it&amp;#8217;s classfied!) to give The Player a bit of a challenge. So, the player goes about creating documents, &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/huddle-apis/wiki/DocumentApprovals#Updating_Assignees_of_the_approvals&quot;&gt;assigning them to The Boss&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/huddle-apis/wiki/Share&quot;&gt;sharing them with him&lt;/a&gt; as well as other document-related actions which The Player needs to experiment with to find out the best strategy. He also enlists the help of his Friend(s) to do the same, and soon The Report starts to be overtaken by other documents on The Boss&amp;#8217;s reccommendations list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it&amp;#8217;s not over yet &amp;#8211; The Player also has Enemies in the office. There&amp;#8217;s that guy who&amp;#8217;s always held a grudge against The Player for getting that raise over him, and the woman who wasn&amp;#8217;t invited to The Player&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;NYE&lt;/span&gt; party when everybody else on their floor was. They all want The Player to be fired, so throughout the day these NPCs will do stuff with The Report which help raise it&amp;#8217;s recommendation score and thus bring it further up in The Boss&amp;#8217;s memory. The Player either has to distract them by assigning them documents or &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/huddle-apis/wiki/Task#Create_a_task&quot;&gt;tasks&lt;/a&gt;, or just try harder to keep other documents above The Report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of the day, if The Report is still in The Boss&amp;#8217;s memory, it&amp;#8217;s Game Over for The Player.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Multiplayer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There could be even more scope for this &amp;#8211; if there are multiple Players, the aim could be to keep your Opponents&amp;#8217; documents &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; The Boss&amp;#8217;s memory and keep yours &lt;em&gt;out&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RPG&lt;/span&gt; mode&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of having a goal, the game could in fact just be used as an interface to Huddle. Instead of logging onto the website every day, a Huddle user could boot up the game and find themselves outside of a huge office building. When they walk into it, they see a few doors, each one representing a &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/huddle-apis/wiki/Workspace&quot;&gt;Workspace&lt;/a&gt; of which they are a member &amp;#8211; they walk into one and see an office. On the wall of each of these offices is a &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/huddle-apis/wiki/WorkspaceCalendar&quot;&gt;calendar&lt;/a&gt; showing the user what tasks they have to complete, and an array of filing cabinets which represent &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/huddle-apis/wiki/Folder&quot;&gt;folders.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The user could go into folders, pick up documents and then go to other folders and drop them, which would cause Huddle to perform a &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/huddle-apis/wiki/Document#Move_a_document&quot;&gt;document move.&lt;/a&gt; The user could also pick&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a huge corridor full of other users&amp;#8217; &amp;#8220;offices&amp;#8221; through which the user could &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/huddle-apis/wiki/Share&quot;&gt;share&lt;/a&gt; a document, or &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/huddle-apis/wiki/Task#Create_a_task&quot;&gt;assign to them a task.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over time, users could be awarded points for approving documents which they have been assigned to in time for the due date, or for making insightful comments on &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/huddle-apis/wiki/WhiteboardComments&quot;&gt;whiteboards&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/huddle-apis/wiki/Task#Add_a_Comment_to_a_Task&quot;&gt;tasks&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/huddle-apis/wiki/DocumentComments&quot;&gt;documents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why not? It&amp;#8217;s quite fun and interesting to think up and attempt new ways to interact with systems which already have a sort of standard way to be interacted with. Public APIs &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be exploited in novel and innovative ways that differ greatly from the way that the app they were created for already does, otherwise you might as well just use the app.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Huddle's Hack Day</title>
   <link href="http://www.danielhough.co.uk/blog/huddle-hack-day"/>
   <updated>2012-04-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://www.danielhough.co.uk/blog/huddle-hack-day</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;top&quot;&gt;Huddle&amp;#8217;s Hack Day&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;meta&quot;&gt;Published 24 April 2012 in London, UK&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only interested in the results? Click &lt;a href=&quot;#results&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Only interested in hack day advice? Click &lt;a href=&quot;#advice&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jamespipe&quot;&gt;James Pipe&lt;/a&gt; approached me with an idea that had been done many times, by many startups and other organisations for many themes, but never by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huddle.com&quot;&gt;Huddle&lt;/a&gt;: a hack day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, I felt a mixture of excitement and skepticism. I&amp;#8217;d only been with Huddle for about seven months, and I&amp;#8217;d never organised a hack day before &amp;#8211; hell, I&amp;#8217;d never even organised a hack hour. The most I&amp;#8217;d ever organised for Huddle&amp;#8217;s Product Engineering team was a day when everyone came in with suits on to poke a bit of fun at our excellent and very well-dressed sales team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Okay,&amp;#8221; I said, &amp;#8220;let&amp;#8217;s do it.&amp;#8221; And I decided that I&amp;#8217;d squash all the skepticism with excitement. The planning began, and we roped &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/#!/holytshirt&quot;&gt;Toby&lt;/a&gt; in to giving us some advice since he&amp;#8217;d done this sort of thing before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, we made a few key decisions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Huddle-only: we&amp;#8217;re both new to this so let&amp;#8217;s keep it in the family this time, and restrict hacks to involve Huddle somehow&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;We need prizes&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;12 hours &amp;#8211; 10am to 10pm&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Encourage people to leave their team-organising until the last minute&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Jagerbombs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from that, we sort-of hoped that this whole thing would work itself out. We decided to hold the hack day on Tuesday, the 3rd of March 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon, we had worked out what we needed to do and had given ourselves tasks. James worked out the budget, marketing (a poster with a list of buzzwords for inspiration) and timings, and I worked out the technical requirements (a single Gist detailing how to make a reverse-proxy in Node.JS for our &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/huddle-apis/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;API&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), acted as the official pep squad whilst James went on holiday, and maintaining the countdown post-its on the posters. All very organised. The day came, we had a claxon to sound when the games began (whom we named Erik Claxon), we had lots of snacks, drinks and we even had some healthy fruit. We were ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ideas&quot;&gt;Ideas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We invited the rest of the company to submit their ideas to a huge whiteboard on post-it notes the Monday night before. The response was unprecedented from Sales, Marketing, Customer Engagement, Product and Corporate. In total we collected over 50 independent ideas on the whiteboard. Some were ridiculous, and actually would have been great hacks had we more time, such as sound effects when you click things, or customiseable backgrounds a-la MySpace. Most of them, however, are genuine ideas for features and improvements that although they might not be suitable for a hack day, will make great Tuesday Time (inspired by Google&amp;#8217;s 20% Time) fodder. We were blown away by the enthusiasm from the rest of the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, Tuesday morning came and the development team, as well as a few of the non-devs who had submitted their ideas, gathered in the Huddle kitchen to be briefed and for an opportunity to &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elevator_pitch&quot;&gt;elevator pitch&lt;/a&gt; their ideas to the rest of the team. And then, the scramble for teams began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results &amp;amp; Voting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was pretty exciting getting our teams worked out. There was a fair amount of winking, nudging and general attempts at convincing the people you wanted if you had an idea of your own, and in the end everybody ended up in a team they liked, or going on their own with only a vision and a vague idea of implementation. Once we&amp;#8217;d all gone through an epic and manic day of furiously programming, eating and drinking, we headed home for some much needed rest and re-adjourned in the morning for the demo to the rest of the company. The hacks were judged by four individuals within Huddle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CEO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One Junior account manager&lt;br /&gt;
One Salesperson&lt;br /&gt;
One Development manager&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an X-Factor style Q&amp;amp;A/critique session, they got all the info they needed and had a private chat after all the demos had finished to decide the winner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I can&amp;#8217;t actually divulge any of the results publicly on the interwebs (except mine, but I&amp;#8217;ll do that in a later blog post), I can tell you that what some of our Huddlers came up with was pretty great. We had a wide range of things, from useful changes to the app, some awesome in-house tools for us to play with and a game based on the Huddle &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;API&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;advice&quot;&gt;Advice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it was our first hack day, there&amp;#8217;s not a huge amount of advice I can give you, and of course next time there&amp;#8217;ll be a lot more to learn still. But for the time being, here&amp;#8217;s what I have to offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t scrimp on the pizza: it&amp;#8217;s much better to have way more, than to have way too little, or you&amp;#8217;ll end up with hungry, tired devs.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Get an appropriate amount of booze for the size of your team and the length of your hack day/hackathon, and the day on which it takes place. For a 16-person hack day over 10 hours, on a week day&amp;#8230; 60 bottles of beer and a big-ass bottle of Jagermeister is probably too much. If it had been on a weekend, we probably would&amp;#8217;ve needed more. So, check yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Record &lt;strong&gt;everything&lt;/strong&gt;: Get some kind of camcorder &amp;#8211; a flipcam works well &amp;#8211; and take some good photos on a still camera. People who couldn&amp;#8217;t attend will want to see some footage &amp;#8211; especially of the demo.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Include everybody, somehow: There&amp;#8217;s no need to limit your hack day to include just contributions from technical staff. Include sales, marketing, customer support and admin at least in contributing ideas &amp;#8211; get them to pitch if they want to! Our non-tech staff had a great time. Plus, if anybody feels they can make even more of a contribution, why shouldn&amp;#8217;t they?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Forbid people from getting their ideas &amp;amp; teams started before the day &amp;#8211; but don&amp;#8217;t expect people to follow the rules: You can&amp;#8217;t expect people to not think about what they want to do and who they want to work with, but discourage them from doing too much organisation before they need to. If they overthink an idea it could spiral out of the control before they&amp;#8217;ve even started working on it &amp;#8211; it&amp;#8217;s better that they keep their ambitions reasonable at the beginning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;tl;dr&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a huge effort from everybody involved, but completely worth it. We left it as open as possible and tried to encourage on-the-spot thinking, and recorded as much as we could. Some great ideas surfaced and some impressive implementations were done with such a limited time, and we all had a great time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important thing to remember is that this is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; supposed to be a trick to get staff to do free work out of hours. It&amp;#8217;s supposed to be open, and fun, and encourage creative thinking, and if some good, shippable stuff comes out of it, that&amp;#8217;s just a bonus.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>